Finding Aid for Hoffius Family Papers, 1919-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hoffius Family Papers 1919-2003
Hoffius family.
04130 Aa 2; UAm
Cornelius Hoffius (1881-1943) and Stuart Hoffius (1914 - ), his son, practiced law in Grand Rapids, and both served as Kent County Prosecuting Attorney. Both men are best known for their respective tenures as Kent County Circuit Court Judges. Stuart Hoffius served as Chief Judge from 1976 until his retirement in 1988. Papers in the collection include personal correspondence, campaign files, speeches, and files documenting involvement with civic, service, and professional organizations, as well as some case files and judicial opinions.
5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
1 film reel 16mm
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Papers were donated by Stuart Hoffius (Donor No. 9487 ) on July 14, 2004.
The collection is open to research.
Cornelius Hoffius was born on August 5, 1881, in Goes, The Netherlands. His family settled in Grand Rapids, Michigan when he was seven years old. He graduated from Grand Rapids Central High School in 1900. Hoffius worked for the Grand Rapids Press, first as a newsboy and later as a reporter. He attended the University of Michigan Law School in Ann Arbor, and graduated with the class of 1904. From 1905 to 1907, he served as assistant prosecuting attorney for Kent County. Hoffius married Rose Kas, and they had one son, Stuart Hoffius, who was born on July 14, 1914. Hoffius was elected prosecuting attorney in 1916, and served in that capacity until 1925. In his private practice, Hoffius was known to have been associated with Theodore H. Elferdink, Dorr Kuizema, and Russell Van Kovering. Hoffius ran for circuit court judge in 1938 while recuperating from a heart attack, and won in the election that November. He finished the incomplete term of Judge Willis B Perkins, and was reelected to a full term in 1941. Hoffius died in office on October 26, 1943. During his lifetime, Hoffius was an active member of the Kent County Republican Party, the Lions Club, and the Fountain Street Baptist Church. Two of the better-known cases litigated by his firm are the Johnson Milk Company case and the G. P. Scharl case.
Richard Stuart Hoffius was born on July 14, 1914 in Grand Rapids. He graduated from Grand Rapids Central High School in June of 1931. He attended Colgate University in Hamilton, New York, and graduated in 1935. Hoffius attended the Harvard University Law School in Cambridge, Massachusetts, from 1935 to 1937. He graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1938. Hoffius entered professional practice in his father's law firm in 1939 with his father's partner, Russell Van Kovering. From July of 1942 to December of 1945, Hoffius served as a Special Agent of the Federal Bureau of Investigation. He married Barbara Chamberlain of Grand Rapids, and they had two sons, Dirk and Stephen Hoffius. Hoffius was appointed Kent County Prosecuting Attorney in January of 1954, won reelection in 1954 and 1956, and served in that capacity until 1958. In 1959 Hoffius was elected Kent County Circuit Court Judge, and he was reelected in 1966. In 1976, Hoffius again won reelection and was named Chief Circuit Court Judge. He was reelected to the position of Chief Judge in 1982, and served in that capacity until he retired on December 31, 1988. Hoffius has been involved with a number of different civic, service, and professional organizations throughout his lifetime, including the Family Service Association, the Boy Scouts of America, the United Community Services Planning Division Project Development Committee, and the Calder Celebration Committee. He is an active member of the Fountain Street Baptist Church. Hoffius was a prolific orator, having delivered many speeches in Grand Rapids, as well as a number of Independence Day addresses at the Pt. Nipigon Resort in the northern Lower Peninsula.
This collection documents the careers, professional lives, and to a lesser extent, the personal lives of two prominent Grand Rapids jurists. The collection is particularly strong in its coverage of the Hoffius campaigns for circuit court judgeships, and their involvement with a number of different professional, civic, and religious organizations. Another strength of the collection lies in its coverage of speeches given by Stuart Hoffius, and associated supporting material. Also of interest in the collection is its representation of life during the Great Depression through the correspondence of Cornelius Hoffius. A few cases handled by the Hoffius family law firm, and several judicial opinions given by Cornelius Hoffius are included with the collection as well.
Papers associated with Cornelius Hoffius were produced between 1919 and 1943; the bulk of them were produced between 1926 and 1943. Papers associated with Stuart Hoffius were produced between 1930 and 2003; the bulk of them were produced between 1949 and 1992. The papers are organized into two series, Personal Papers and Business Files.
Subjects:
Hoffius family.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Kent County (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Hoffius, Cornelius, 1881-1943.; Lawyers--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Hoffius, Stuart, 1914-; Judges--Michigan--Kent County.
Contributors:
Hoffius, Cornelius, 1881-1943.; Hoffius, Stuart, 1914-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Personal Papers
  The Personal Papers series is divided into two subseries. The first contains the personal papers of Cornelius Hoffius. These are arranged topically, in alphabetical order. The second subseries contains the personal papers of Stuart Hoffius. These are arranged topically, in groups, which include Civic Organizations/Activities; Other Organizations/Activities; Professional Organizations/Activities; Speeches, Independence Day; and Speeches, General. This subseries is also arranged in alphabetical order throughout, except for the Independence Day Speeches group of files, which is arranged chronologically.
  - Cornelius Hoffius
    - Biographical Clippings 1919, 1922, 1938, Undated (Box 1)
    - Campaign for Kent County Circuit Court Judge 1938
      (see also oversize campaign poster UAm)
      - Republican Primary Election (Box 1)
      - General Election, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1927, 1929-1943, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Fountain Street Baptist Church
      - General 1935-1936 (Box 1)
      - Music Committee 1934-1938 (Box 1)
    - Lions Club 1941-1942, Undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs (University of Michigan Law School class reunions), Undated (Box 1)
    - Politics 1939-1941, Undated (Box 1)
    - Speeches Undated (Box 1)
  - R. Stuart Hoffius
    - Civic Organizations/Activities
      - Calder Celebration Committee 1993-1995, 3 folders (Box 2)
        include photographs
      - Family Service Association 1948-1959, 9 folders (Box 2)
      - United Community Services Planning Division Project Development Committee 1960 (Box 2)
    - Other Organizations/Activities
      - Boy Scouts of America, Grand Valley Council 1949-1951 (Box 2)
      - Campaign 1954, 1956, 1959, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - Colgate University Alumni 1949-1960 (Box 2)
      - Colgate University Fund Drive 1949-1951, 1959 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1954-1956, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1957-1960, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Fountain Street Baptist Church 1949-1951, 1957-1959, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Helios (Grand Rapids Central High School student publication) 1930-1931, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Society of Former Special Agents of the FBI 1957 (Box 3)
    - Professional Organizations/Activities
      - Committee on Domestic Relations 1953-1954 (Box 3)
      - Criminal Jurisprudence Committee 1956-1960 (Box 3)
      - Disorderly Persons Committee 1954 (Box 3)
      - Divorce Seminar 1980-1981 (Box 3)
      - Insurance Law Seminar 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Speeches, Independence Day (Pt. Nipigon Resort)
      - Compilation Book Project (Dirk and Stephen Hoffius) 1976-2002 (Box 3)
      - 1989 Supreme Court, 1989, 1991-1993, Undated (Box 3)
      - 1991 Constitution, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
      - 1992 Declaration of Independence, 1941, 1987, 1990-1991, 1993-1994, Undated (Box 3)
      - 1996George Washington, 1995, 1996, Undated (Box 3)
      - 1997 Mackinac Bridge, 1997 (Box 3)
      - 1998 Thomas Jefferson, 1998 (Box 3)
      - 1999 Soo Locks, 1999 (Box 3)
      - 2000 Fr. Marquette, 2000, Undated (Box 3)
      - 2001 Cheboygan 2001, Undated (Box 3)
      - 2002 John Adams, 2002 (Box 3)
      - 2003 Arlington National Cemetery, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Speeches, General
      - American Foreign Policy 1984 (Box 3)
      - Changes in the Law 1985, 1987 (Box 3)
      - Chappaquidick: Fact or Fiction? 1971, Undated (Box 3)
      - The Courts and Crime Deterence 1976-1977 (Box 3)
      - Crime and Its Impact on Society 1978, Undated (Box 3)
      - Criminal Code 1967-1968, 1970, 1972, Undated (Box 3)
      - Diversion Program 1973-1974 (Box 4)
      - Emeritus, Calvin College 1991-1992, Undated (Box 4)
      - Ethics, Bar and Bench 1987 (Box 4)
      - Europe 1964, 1966 (Box 4)
      - Grand Jury 1967, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Grand Rapids Foundation 1986 (Box 4)
      - Judge Starr Dedication 1983 (Box 4)
      - Judging Business 1980, 1981, Undated (Box 4)
      - Judicial Seminar 1964-1979, Undated, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - Kosten, Edward A 1954, Undated (Box 4)
      - Law Day 1935-1989, Undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Law and Media 1979, 1981-1984, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Medical Malpractice 1978, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous 1959-1962, 1969, Undated (Box 4)
      - Naturalization 1984 (Box 4)
      - Opinion Writing (Judicial) 1974 (Box 4)
      - Organized Crime 1969-1972 (Box 4)
      - Police Academy 1970, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Sawyer, Harold 2003 (Box 4)
      - Segregation 1958, Undated (Box 4)
      - Settlement of Cases and Pre-Trials 1963, 1965, 1981, 1984 (Box 4)
      - Sexual Harassment 1989, 1991, 1992, Undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Smith, Bud Undated (Box 4)
      - Supreme Court 1958, 1964, 1966, 1970, Undated (Box 4)
      - Walsh, Tom, Rotary Award 1985 (Box 4)
      - Watergate 1974-1975 (Box 4)
- Business Files
  The second series in the collection consists of Business Files. This series contains files produced in the normal transaction of business by Cornelius and Stuart Hoffius in a professional or official capacity. The Business Files series is arranged into three subseries. The first subseries, entitled "Law Firm" contains case files produced by the Hoffius law firm, which was known as Hoffius and Van Kovering for a time, but was probably known by another name or names as well over the course of its existence. Two of the three clients represented in this subseries were also known by different names over the course of their history. The Christian Psychiatric Hospital was also known (or at least referred to within the firm) as the Cutlerville Asylum, and later changed its name to Pine Rest Sanatarium. The Johnson Milk Company was known as the Modern Milk Company until 1936 or 1937. The second subseries contains the papers of Cornelius Hoffius produced in an official capacity during his tenure as Kent County Circuit Court Judge. These include official correspondence, and judicial opinions; particularly ones Hoffius used as models for writing his own opinions. The third and last subseries contains a few papers produced (or acquired) by Stuart Hoffius during his tenure as Kent County Circuit Court Judge.
  - Law Firm
    - Christian Psychiatric Hospital, Cutlerville
      - Cutlerville Asylum 1935-1937 (Box 5)
      - Christian Psychiatric Hospital 1935-1938, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Johnson Milk Company
      - Modern Milk Company 1932-1936, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Johnson Milk Company 1937-1941, Undated, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Ottawas and Chippewas 1926 (Box 5)
      (This case concerned the disbursement of funds to qualified individuals under the terms of a treaty made July 31, 1855 and subsequent related legislation. Included in the file is an "Indian Land Certificate" dated December 19, 1865.)
    - G. P. Scharl 1926, 1927, 1932, 1936, Undated, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Cornelius Hoffius, Kent County Circuit Court Judge
    - Correspondence 1939-1943 (Box 5)
    - Opinions, Judicial 1939-1943, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - R. Stuart Hoffius, Kent County Circuit Court Judge
    - Miscellaneous 1971, 1980 (Box 5)
- 1 motion picture
  (staff use only)